<chapter>
<title>Creating a Document based application</title>
  <para>
    A document based application is an application that has a
    specific file type associated with it that it edits.
  </para>
  <para>
   A document based application has the following features.
   <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>Creates a new document when clicking on the iconbar</listitem>
     <listitem>Loads a document if it is dropped on the iconbar</listitem>
     <listitem>Opens a document if it is double clicked in the filer</listitem>
     <listitem>Shows a window with the document contents</listitem>
     <listitem>Updates the title of the window with the filename and a "*" if a document is modified</listitem>
     <listitem>Shows a SaveAs window to allowing saving of the file</listitem>
     <listitem>Shows the Discard/Cancel/Save dialogue when trying to close a window with modified content</listitem>
     <listitem>Shows the Quit dialogue if you try to quit the application with unsaved documents</listitem>
     <listitem>Provides a FileInfo window to show details of the current document</listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>To set up a file type for your document you need to add the following entries to your
  <filename>!Boot</filename> and <filename>!Run</filename> files so the Desktop can identify your file type and
  launch your application if it is double clicked upon in the filer.
  <programlisting>
    | Variables need to be added (in this case for TbxDocEx file type hex 010)
    
    | Let the desktop know what to do to edit this file type
    Set Alias$RunType_010 Run &lt;Obey$Dir&gt;.!Run %%*0
    | Set The description for the file type
    Set File$Type_010 "TbxDocEx"    
  </programlisting>
  You will also need to add an icon to your <filename>!Sprites</filename> file for display in the filer.
  This is the usual 34x17 sprite the same size as your application sprite, but with the
  name file_XXX where XXX is your file type number. (In the above example it would be file_010).
  </para>
  <para>
    tbx provides a group of classes to provide a framework in the <package>tbx::doc</package> namespace
    for all of this standard functionality. You do not have
    to use this framework, you can instead add listeners to the application for the WIMP messages
    you need to process for this type of application and the necessary toolbox objects and functionality.
  </para>
  <para>
    To use the <package>tbx::doc</package> classes you need to create and add the following
    resources to your <filename>Res</filename>.
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>An Iconbar named "Iconbar"</listitem>
      <listitem>A main Window (the name of it is passed to the DocWindow constructor)</listitem>
      <listitem>A SaveAs dialogue called "SaveAs"</listitem>
      <listitem>A DCS dialogue called "DCS"</listitem>
      <listitem>A Quit dialogue called "Quit"</listitem>
      <listitem>A FileInfo dialogue called "FileInfo"</listitem>
      <listitem>An icon bar menu with at least the Quit option</listitem>
      <listitem>A menu for the main window that has entries to show the SaveAs and FileInfo windows</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    You then add the following code to you <function>main</function> function.
    <programlisting>
      tbx::Application docex_app("&lt;TbxDocEx$Dir&gt;");
      tbx::doc::DocCreator&lt;TbxExDoc, TbxExWnd&gt; doc_creator(0x010);
      tbx::doc::DocManager doc_manager(&amp;doc_creator);
      tbx::doc::DocIconbar doc_iconbar;
      tbx::doc::DocSaveAs doc_saveas;
      tbx::doc::DocFileInfo doc_fileinfo;

      if (argc > 1) doc_manager.load_files(argc-1, argv+1);

      docex_app.run();
    </programlisting>
    In the above listing the following would be replaced with items for your application.
    TbxDocEx$Dir would be replaced with the path name for your resources.
    <classname>TbxExDoc</classname> would be your document class (derived
    from <classname>tbx::doc::Document</classname>).
    <classname>TbxExWnd</classname> would be
    your class to handle the display of the document (derived from <classname>tbx::doc::DocWindow</classname>).
  </para>
  <para>
    With this code in place all that is then needed is to derive your document from <classname>tbx::doc::Document</classname>
    (TbxExDoc in the example code above) and overload the <methodname>document_size</methodname>,
    <methodname>load(std::istream &amp;is)</methodname> and <methodname>save(std::ostream &amp;os)</methodname>
    methods.
  </para>
  <para>
     The window to display the document should be derived from tbx::doc::DocWindow
     and modified to show the data when it is created.
    </para>
  <para>
    If more functionality is required from the iconbar you may want to derive
    a class from <classname>tbx::doc::DocIconbar</classname> as well.
  </para>
  <para>
    There is a demo application called !TbxDocEx included in the separate TBX-Examples download
    that shows a simple document based application.
  </para>
</chapter>
